Preliminary Guide to the Bernard I. Duffey Papers, 1957 - 1983
Duke University. University Archives
Bernard I. Duffey papers 1957 - 1983
Duffey, Bernard I., 1917-
1.0 linear feet Extent: 1,000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Bernard I. Duffey worked as an author and Professor of English at Duke University. Papers include correspondence, notebooks, memoranda, minutes, committee notes, course materials, manuscript materials and research notes. Major subjects include Bernard I. Duffey, Duke University, Duke University's Department of English curriculum, the Duke University Press, Program II, and study and teaching of American literature and poetry. Materials range in date from 1957-1983. Contains restricted materials. English.
UA.29.02.0047
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Bernard I. Duffey Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974 and 1988.
Biographical Note
Bernard I. Duffey received his bachelor's degree from Oberlin College and his master's and doctoral degrees from Ohio State University. Duffey began his career teaching at Michigan State University and the University of Minnesota.
In 1963, he joined the Duke University English Department, where he taught American poetry and contemporary American literature. He received a Fulbright scholarship to teach at the University of Copenhagen in 1970, and was also a visiting professor at the University of California at Irvine. Duffey was chair of the English Department Courses and Curriculum Committee and served on a variety of committees and boards at Duke University: the Committee on Teacher Evaluation and Learning Process, Program II Committee, and the Duke University Press Editorial Advisory Board.
Duffey's writings include: Modern American Literature (1951), The Chicago Renaissance in American Letters (1956), Poetry in America: Expression and its Values in the Times of Bryant, Whitman, and Pound (1978), Chicago's Public Wits; a Chapter in the American Comic Spirit (1983), and A Poetry of Presence: the Writing of William Carlos Williams (1986). One of his essays was published in The Comic Imagination in American Literature (1973), a collection about the sources of humor in literature.
Bernard I. Duffey, professor emeritus of English, died in 1994.
Collection Overview
Contains materials pertaining to the professional work of Bernard I. Duffey, author and Professor of English at Duke University. Papers include correspondence, notebooks, memoranda, minutes, committee notes, course materials, manuscript materials and research notes. Major subjects include Bernard I. Duffey, Duke University, Duke University's Department of English curriculum, the Duke University Press, Program II, and study and teaching of American literature and poetry. Materials range in date from 1957-1983. Contains restricted materials.
Subject Headings
American literature -- 20th century -- Study and teaching (Higher); American poetry -- 20th century -- Study and teaching (Higher); Duffey, Bernard I., 1917-; Duke University. Dept. of English -- Curricula; Duke University. Dept. of English -- Faculty; Duke University Press; Duke University. Program II
Contents of Collection
- Container List:
  - Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - English Department Committees, ca. 1965-1973
    - Courses and Curriculum Committee (Box 1)
    - Graduate Student - Faculty Committee (Box 1)
  - Student evaluation of teachers, form construction materials (Box 1)
  - Undergraduate Faculty Council of the Arts and Sciences, ca. 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Courses in contemporary American literature and poetry, course materials, syllabi (Box 1)
  - Program II
    - Applications (Box 1)
      NOTE: Program II Applications and other student records are RESTRICTED.
    - General advisory committee materials (Box 1)
  - Duke University Press board, ca. 1981 (Box 1)
  - Research notebooks
    - Poetics of Nature (Box 1)
    - Encounter and Irresolution (Box 1)
  - Some Elements of Narrative, unpublished manuscript, 1981 (Box 1)
Related Material
Dept. of English records.
University Archives, Duke University.